so in terms of
anapanasati mindfulness of
breath we
spoke uh recently
about uh the wrong views around
that but what so what it what did the
Buddha teach what did he mean by
mindfulness of
breathing uh how is it done in in the
right sense and I have a Sut and I'll just
sense and I have a Sut and I'll just
read a little bit of it it's from the
samut nikaya
54.6 and this is to
arita and the Buddha asks the monks do
you cultivate
mindfulness of the in andout breathing
do you cultivate recollection of that of
the
bread and venerable arita replied to the
blessed one I cultivate mindfulness of
breathing
but how do you cultivate mindfulness of
breathing arita and then arita says this short
arita and then arita says this short
verse having let go of desire for past
and future sensual pleasures and having
thoroughly subdued perceptions of
resistance with regard to internal and
external events I knowingly breathe in
and I knowingly breathe
out and the Buddha says there is that
mindfulness of breathing but this is a
detailed approach which brings such a
practice to fulfillment so he's agreeing
with arita and then saying let me give
you the detailed yeah let me give you
the the thorough one yeah they would
they would make it well they will
fulfill it completely yeah and just to
point out you know when he's talking
about mindfulness he's not talking about he's
mindfulness he's not talking about he's
talking about right mindfulness that
which has the right view well yeah
mindful well there you go like even
mindfulness just to start with that term
it's not focusing you're not mindful
when you're focusing on sensations of
your breath you're mindful when you're
not forgetful so it's non forgetfulness of
forgetful so it's non forgetfulness of
your breathing that's the practice non
forgetfulness of of a of a dynamic
reference point that is here and now
whether you want it to be or
not um so well again because we might
have people listening this V uh this
this particular video without listening
the previous ones as anapanasati suta
says um the anapanasati was Tau
basically to monks that were at least
sought upon
us so practicing non forgetfulness of
breathing as a right reference point
would then calm your mind rightly and
bring your right view to
fulfillment so the Buddha never went to
householder and taught them anapanasati
just after he offered the meal he taught
him meditation technique and then went
back to the forest or something never
ever happened Unthinkable so it so what
you're saying and what I'm hearing you
know is that you can use the
breath for Co for your development of
Right View once you have a certain way
of
seeing well yeah once you know what the
dhama is then you can use the breath the
body the post the for panas whatever
exactly cultivate that Divine but again
using them through non forgetfulness not
through focusing on sensations of that
that's the opposite of where your memory
is you forget everything else when
you're focusing hard on something of an
object of your perception so it's
completely the opposite
direction and um and and that's that's
the whole point like you don't need more
detailed instruction than what the suta
says knowingly you breathe in knowingly
you breathe out
that's that's already in fact the
details well can you do that why why is
that not clear why do you need more
specific description is it because you expect the
description is it because you expect the
practice to be different or you want it
to be tactile observations that you used
to so then saying knowingly you breathe
in knowingly breathe out it's just like
kind of too abstract basically divorce or
of too abstract basically divorce or
what does that even mean what means that
knowingly you breathe in can you breathe
in and out without forgetting that you
were breathing in and out without
attending it directly you're breathing
in and out because you can be breathing
in and out without attending it that's
what you're doing most of your time you
don't need to attend to your breathing
in order to
breathe it's already there so can you
access that which is already there
through your memory through the
knowledge of it being already there
happening like this or like this but not
through your directly attending and
trying to manipulate and and observe and
say closely up expecting magic to come
out of
them or use it to forget about
everything else so using it as a reference point it
else so using it as a reference point it
it's it's a knowledge knowledge of a
dynamic reference
point that if you learn how to um
maintain cultivate without falling into
directly attending it you are developing
it and why is it important to not
directly attend it
because when you directly attend things
it always has to be done at the expense
of something
else always but if you're learning to not
always but if you're learning to not
forget things that are already there
that's how you get the bigger picture
that's how you actually start to include
everything more specific that's
occurring to you
now at the same time
so it's mindfulness of breathing not
sensation watching of your
breath and even just
as this is to the
monks and as a arita points out he's let
go of desire for past and future central
place yes like I I don't think I I don't
think that most of people don't even
recognize the implications of what AR
said he abandoned the desire for past
and future Central
Pleasures somebody might wonder how your
band desire for past is already gone but
you realize if you're not free From
centrality Here and Now past Central
Pleasures are still
Central remembering past Central
Pleasures imply desire that you're not
free from wishing for future Central
Pleasures imply a desire that you not
free from here and now but if you're
free from any desire Here and Now for
Central Pleasures through and through as
that framework of your intention is
purified From Desire towards sensual
Pleasures even past Pleasures that you
used to enjoy will not be seen essential
will not be felt essential Here and Now
anymore and you certainly will not be
craving for the future
ones and how did he abandon that but
then he says in the next line he
abandoned resistance towards anything
and everything internally or externally
that might occur so there is no
resistance there is no paa there is no
aversion means he has been developed in
regard to his own body sufficiently
enough that the resistance on account of
discomfort would not be inducing
thoughts of
sensuality so he stopped
resisting as a result of that the main
coping mechanism of dealing with
mechanism of dealing with
pain has been abandoned and Main coping
mechanism of dealing with pain is
sensuality as the Sut said that
before like an untrained mind when
touched with unpleasant feeling does
know does not know any other escape from
that feeling except sensual desire
replacing it with pleasure of
sensuality that is at its roote so if
you stop cultivating that resistance if
you overcome it if you train yourself in
regard to it when this Comfort touches
you you don't resist it internally nor
externally you certainly don't act out
it that would have been developed way
before the desire to cover it up through
the pleasure of Senses will also fade
and then you will have no desire to
sensuality because the main purpose for
that sensuality that that existed is now
abandoned it's
gone so if a mind has developed that
then you can now practice the knowledge
of your in andout breath not before
because if you're trying to get away
from your situation cover it up cover up
the pain with sensuality and so on how
are you going
to be aware or knowing you know know the
greater context see what's actually
going on remember what is present no
exactly exactly yeah it's a loss of
perspective focusing is a loss of
perspective intentional intentional
diminishing of perspective cuz
perspective is
painful so you focus so that everything
else just just just disappears
sensuality The Act of sensual running
away from from discomfort that touches
you exactly